你可能从没注意过
You probably never noticed this
苹果的官方配件
Apple's official accessories
AirPodsMax一个
A pair of AirPodsMax
4399 yuan
蓝牙鼠标MagicMouse
The bluetooth mouse MagicMouse
一根编织充电线
A braided charging cable
这些东西的硬件成本
The hardware cost of all these things
业内估算不到标价的15%
Industry estimates put it under 15% of the retail price
剩下85%是什么
What's the other 85%
是那只苹果logo附带的心理税
It's the psychological tax that comes with the Apple logo
你买配件的时候不犹豫
You don't hesitate when buying accessories
因为反正都用iPhone了
Because you already use an iPhone anyway
配套要苹果的
So you want Apple accessories to match
这就是品牌溢价的网状效应
This is the network effect of brand premium
它不是只在一个产品上收你钱
They don't just charge you on one product
是在你整个生态里
They charge you across your entire ecosystem
每一处都收你一点
A little bit everywhere
苹果一年从配件上赚的钱
How much Apple makes from accessories in a year
超过400亿美元
Over 40 billion dollars
这400亿
This 40 billion
全是从你反正都买了那一秒的犹豫里
All squeezed out of that one second of hesitation when you think
一笔一笔抠出来的
I've already bought it anyway
讲了这么多陷阱
So many traps discussed
怎么破
How do we break them
我给你3个方法
I'll give you 3 methods
下次买手机的时候拿出来用
Pull them out next time you buy a phone
第一个方法
The first method
叫功能清单法
Is called the feature checklist
买之前
Before you buy
写下你真正每天用手机做什么
Write down what you actually use your phone for every day
打电话
Making calls
发微信
Sending WeChat messages
刷视频
Scrolling videos
拍娃
Taking photos of your kid
然后一条条对
Then check them one by one
5000块以下的手机能不能做
Can a phone under 5000 do all of that
能
Yes
那你多花的部分
Then the extra you spend
是为爽和身份付的钱
Is paying for the feeling and status
你愿意付
If you're willing to pay
不是问题
That's fine
但你得清楚自己在为什么付
But you need to know what you're paying for
第二个方法
The second method
叫二手价测试
Is called the resale value test
打开闲鱼
Open Xianyu
搜一下你想买的那款
Search for the model you want to buy
看一年后能卖多少钱
See how much it sells for after one year
iPhone15ProMax用一年
An iPhone15ProMax after one year
能卖8000
Can sell for 8000
折损5000
That's 5000 in depreciation
小米15Ultra用一年
A Xiaomi 15Ultra after one year
能卖3500
Can sell for 3500
折损3000
That's 3000 in depreciation
你为身份信号多付了2000块
You paid 2000 more for the status signal
这不一定是亏
This isn't necessarily a loss
但你得知道账是怎么算的
But you should know how the math works
第三个方法
The third method
叫24小时冷静期
Is called the 24-hour cooldown
看上一款手机
When you spot a phone you like
别马上下单
Don't order right away
回家睡一觉
Go home and sleep on it
第二天早上再问自己一次
Ask yourself again the next morning
我真的需要它吗
Do I really need it
不是我想要
Not do I want it
是我需要
Do I need it
这两个词之间
Between these two words
差的就是凡勃伦效应给你下的迷魂药
Lies the poison the Veblen effect feeds you
我给你模拟一个场景
Let me set up a scenario for you
你预算6000
Your budget is 6000
本来想买标准版
You originally wanted the standard model
店员把你引到ProMax前面
The salesperson leads you to the ProMax
你心跳加快
Your heart starts racing
觉得加3000就能拥有顶配
You feel like just 3000 more gets you the top tier
这时候
At this moment
你该做什么
What should you do
出门
Walk out
散步十分钟
Take a ten-minute walk
打开你的功能清单
Open your feature checklist
你需要1TB吗
Do you need 1TB
不需要
No
你需要钛合金边框吗
Do you need a titanium frame
不需要
No
你需要那个微距镜头吗
Do you need that macro lens
一年用不到3次
You'd use it less than 3 times a year
走回店里
Walk back into the store
买你原本要买的标准版
Buy the standard model you originally planned
省下来的3000
The 3000 you saved
存进定期
Put it in a fixed deposit
一年的利息够你买一对AirPods
One year of interest is enough for a pair of AirPods
你算一下
Do the math
每次换手机省3000
Save 3000 every time you switch phones
10年就是3万
That's 30000 in 10 years
这3万存进指数基金
Put that 30000 in an index fund
按年化7%
At 7% annual return
30年后是22万
In 30 years it becomes 220000
凡勃伦效应让你看不见这条线
The Veblen effect makes you blind to this path
而真正的有钱人
While truly wealthy people
从不在凡勃伦效应里
Never fall into the Veblen trap
巴菲特开了20年的福特皮卡
Buffett drove a Ford pickup for 20 years
扎克伯格常年穿灰色T恤
Zuckerberg wears a grey T-shirt all year round
上班骑自行车
And rides a bike to work
他们不需要手机告诉别人自己是谁
They don't need a phone to tell others who they are
其实关于贵这件事
Actually about things being expensive
最核心的真相只有一句
The core truth comes down to one sentence
价格不等于价值
Price does not equal value
你看到的标价
The price tag you see
是商家想让你以为的价值
Is the value the seller wants you to believe
真正的价值
The real value
是这个东西在你的生活里能做什么
Is what this thing can actually do in your life
当你能分清这两者的时候
When you can tell the two apart
你就走出消费陷阱了
You've escaped the consumption trap
不是说一定要买便宜的
It's not about always buying cheap
是要为对你有用的东西付钱
It's about paying for what's actually useful to you
不为让别人羡慕的东西付钱
Not paying for things that make others jealous
最后送你一句话
One last thing for you
最贵的那个选项
The most expensive option
不是给你买的
Isn't there for you to buy
是给你看的
It's there for you to look at
看完之后
After seeing it
请你转身去买那个真正适合你的
Turn around and buy the one that truly fits you
如果今天这条视频对你有启发
If this video inspired you today
点个关注
Hit follow
我每周讲一个经济学故事
I tell one economics story every week
帮你看穿那些每天都在踩
Helping you see through the thinking traps
却从来没注意到的思维陷阱
You step into every day without noticing
你少为logo付的每一笔钱
Every yuan you stop paying for a logo
都是你给自己未来攒下的自由
Is freedom you've saved for your future self
我们下期见
See you next time